[Music]
what we're looking at right now and one
of the reasons I think that the
intellectual dark web has particularly
arisen at this time is that we really
did have the emergence of this new stage
of development and it really is
radically relativistic radically
egalitarian pretty great deal of
emphasis on equal outcome and she's any
differences at all as the product of
oppression or discrimination and that's
what so many of the intellectual dark
web people are fighting against they're
saying look it's it's possible that some
of that is oppression no doubt but
they're also other reasons that we see
these differences and they might have to
do with different interests and male and
female for example some people would say
that that is is a caricature and most
people on the Left don't believe those
things well then here's the question why
is it that this moderate reasonable EFT
doesn't tell these shrill voices to shut
up they're terrified so it's not like
you get you sit down with someone and
automatically you strengthen them
there's no automatic maybe they'll be
strengthened if their ideas are good and
I don't know I'd ever argue that you
shouldn't sit down with someone I think
my main point is whether people are
being challenged enough because and that
goes back to my point before about has
has it shifted because because now there
are expectations I mean we're seeing
this for Joe Rogan I think we're seeing
this with you as well that there are
expectations that you will hold people
to account in a way that when you're an
upstart kind of alternative media
channel yes we're not there right so as
I said earlier but look the bigger you
get the more relevant you get the more
haters are going to come out but the
more that legitimate
we'll come out - and again I address
this all the time what do you think's
the most legitimate criticism it's not
really for me to say what the legitimate
criticism of me if someone wants to say
that they don't like the way I interview
or that I don't ask hard enough
questions or something like that well I
suppose that is a legitimate criticism
of me it's not the way I like doing my
business the nature of the media has
changed so much that once you're looking
at a particular kind of information
source or a certain kind of world you
just get more and more feedback that
supports that view and there's more and
more reason to distrust everybody else
so we're all learning how to distrust
everybody else and to confirm not
conform to our particular worldview and
that arose the sense that there's some
larger consensus reality that's weaving
us together so we're kind of let loose
and this very fragmented
it's like people used to complain about
post-modernism in the 80s and early 90s
it's like no now we're now we're living
in it now we're living real relativism
one of the ideas that led me to his book
maps of meaning early on was just from
reading different philosophers I sort of
came to this conclusion that you can
have two people in the same room you
know in the same place at the same
coffee table in front of them but your
belief system and the way you frame the
world informs reality to the extent
where we can literally be in two
different realities even if we're beside
each other and this was like a big aha
moment for me of well we're kind of
screwed like how can people really
understand each other and resolve
conflicts and I remember that being the
initial thing that somehow led me I
think through some google search to maps
of meaning so it's interesting how I you
know later found myself working on this
film about Jordan's comments on Bill c16
involving into all of this other these
other issues of political correctness
but with with this idea of culture war
looming underneath all of that
I've always been interested in stuff to
do with psychology of almost every kind
and I'm also interested in spiritual
stuff in a very weakened form which is
what I what I call why we're here
is there a purpose of life and of course
the current scientific paradigms there's
no purpose at all consciousness is an
epiphenomenon caused by chemical it's a
chemical reaction which i think is
complete nonsense it reminds me of what
George Orwell once said which was only
an intellectual could believe that there
are two types of hierarchies and this is
what Greene absolutely overlooks and
it's a disaster
there are Dominator hierarchies and
there are growth hierarchies or
actualization hierarchies Dominator
hierarchies are all the horrible things
that postmodern say they are they're
tyrannical their power structures
they're oppressive they're the cause of
almost every nightmare you can think of
in human history and you want to do as
much as you can to get rid of those as
much as you possibly can but then there
are growth hierarchies those are the
opposite of done literally the opposite
of Dominator hierarchies in a dominate
of those the same thing as what Peterson
would describe as hierarchies of
competence close to it the Dominator
hierarchies the higher you go and a
Dominator hierarchy the more people you
can oppress the more people you can hurt
the more exclusive you are the higher
you go in a growth hierarchy the more
inclusive you are you actually are
including more people we saw this simple
developmental model it goes in just me
to a group to all groups to all humans
to integrating all of those that's a
growth highroad
you know I started being like okay Kent
I can't trust news to be true because
news is narrative warfare and I can't
trust science without actually really
looking at what was the methodology
employed how was it funded what were the
axioms that the team was using what were
the logical transforms am i seeing all
of their data or was a cherry pick data
and as we as I started to kind of unfold
to say where are the high signal low
noise sources that I can't offload some
of the cognitive complexity of making
sense of the world to the answer is
really sad right I don't know any
sources that are very high signal and
little noise a across lots of areas so
they don't start being like well why is
that and what would it take to fix that
what would it take to make a world ahead
an intact information ecology well that
requires understanding why the current
information ecology is as broken as it
is and we're starting to touch on a
couple things here but this goes deep
and how do we make good choices if we
don't have good sense mate well
obviously we can't but due to increasing
technological capacity right increasing
population multiplied by increasing
impact per person we're making more and
more consequential choices with worse
and worse sense making to inform those
choices which is kind of running
increasingly fast through the woods
increasingly blind right and so I think
many of the people that you've had on
row wisdom have been in a deep inquiry
around how do we actually fix our own
sense making and it's some of what has
brought us to have conversations with
each other because a part of how we work
with our own sense making as we
recognize the cognitive complexity of
issues that the world faces is more than
a single person can process a single
brain that can't actually hold that
common complexity I hate both phrases
toxic masculinity and toxic femininity
and you know the piece that I wrote for
Colette I think was called on toxic
femininity to to make the point right up
front you know before I got into it and
the piece that the
but this was going to be that
conversation or at least a very small
part of it actually there's there's a
lot a lot more to say about it
which is that men can go violent few of
them do but it's bad women are much less
likely to go physically violent or an
average smaller and not as strong of
course weird I like Lee to have used
physical violence as our weapon right
men are more likely to have used
physical violence as their weapon when
they went violent women are much more
likely to use wiles and sexuality
because especially for young women that
is where their power is and young women
have such vast power over basically
every other demographic at least in
American culture in in some cultures and
you know in the Far East where elders
are respected more this is not this is
not going to be the same kind of dynamic
[Music]
part of me wants to work quietly and
part of me realizes that we have to work
in some public facing capacity and I
personally have found it much more
comfortable to have a private life to
not have everything that I'm thinking
broadcast to a large audience but I
think we've run out of time and so I
think some of us are somewhat
reluctantly choosing to make a different
call now I think that with the current
administration and the White House
you're seeing a real discontinuity with
the past and it wasn't the discontinuity
that I was hoping for we had to break
with the past and I think that the way
in which we are now breaking with the
past is so destructive nobody knows what
to believe nobody quite knows what's
true
nobody knows where to turn this is not a
tenable situation and so either we're
going to descend into some kind of
permanent chaos or there is going to be
have to be something that we reboot from
and that thing cannot be simply left or
simply right and that's one of the
reasons the IDW is hopeful to me well
done for making it to the end I just
wanted to let you know a few things
we've got coming up including the
biggest event we've ever done the rebel
wisdom festival which will be a mix of
ideas and dialogues between people like
Douglas rushkoff Daniel schmeckt and
burger Bonita Roy Rupert Sheldrake Jamba
Vicki and many more and because wisdom
isn't just intellectual it's also about
practice will be offering experiences
like circling different interpersonal
dialogue mindfulness breathwork and many
other with world-class facilitators and
if you're enjoying the content you can
help us make more by joining the rebel
wisdom club which will give you
discounts and the courses and the events
and also access to a load more content
on the website including all of our live
events it'll also give you access to our
growing community which is something we
want to make a real focus for 2020
adding more meetups and other services
for members so hope you enjoyed the film
and see you soon
you